Since I was a child, I felt a strong
attraction to taking apart the devices
that surrounded me: watches, calculators,
blenders, microwaves, televisions, video games,
stereos, washing machines, vacuum cleaners.
Nothing escaped my curiosity. Besides, there was
no one to stop me. My parents worked
almost all day. My brother
Irving and I [dog barks] had several
caregivers and neighbors who looked after us in
their homes. That's how I met Rosalba,
Ruben (her son, "El Pul"), and Anita, her
sister. Over the years, my habit of
taking things apart caused me several
problems, scoldings, and anger from
my parents. One day I took apart a wrist
watch. My father forced me to search
for every last screw, something he never achieved.
They were very difficult to find. The pressure
in my parents' relationship was so
strong that maybe I took everything apart
to understand how things worked
on the inside. It was as if... by dissecting
the inner workings of objects, I could also
understand the tensions at home. As I took
things apart, I began to recognize how the
illusion behind the devices is dismantled.
As a child, I had a toy television
that showed a puppy playing with a ball.
When I opened it,
I found a strip of paper that told the
story of that dog. Moving in front of
a grooved screen created the illusion of a
moving image. Over time, I heard a
neighbor's TV had fallen. I suggested
to my mother that we go see her. While she
was chatting with the neighbor, I took on
the task of investigating inside the broken TV,
hoping to find the Spiderman and
Batman strip.
But I only found circuits that are still
with me today, along with my passion for
cinema. One day, Don Beto, a friend of
my parents and a neighbor exiled from the
Pinochet dictatorship, who worked as an
official at the Politécnico,
brought me a radio to repair. I was about
ten years old. I never repaired it, I broke
it, I removed circuits and burned it. I
think that's where my vocation as an
engineer was revealed, although in a very
peculiar way. Instead of
building, it seemed my path was to
deconstruct to understand, like a hacker
who deciphers the source code of a system.
Now, after returning home,
maybe I have to repair things alongside
my mother and my brother. Looking for ways
to generate income, I thought of opening a
repair shop and selling second-hand items
and music from my friends, stickers, and
t-shirts in the garage.
This is not just a store, it's a
declaration. The idea is to offer
economic alternatives linked to the
recycling and repair of electronic
devices, as well as cultural workshops
for the community. I want to create a
space where what others discard, we
recover and give it a
-new life, a second chance.
-Hello, how are you? We invite you to this
next Thursday, thirty-eighth of... of
March,
um,
HUBLab Laboratory,
to take a-- a kind of workshop, a kind
of course, the
training so you can make a
[electric guitar and trumpet music]